Ann Charters Papers
© 2002 University of Connecticut
Ann Charters Papers.
1966-1982.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Charters, Ann.
5.5 linear feet.
Ann Charters was born 10 November 1936, in Bridgeport, CT, the daughter of Nathan (a contractor) and Kate (Schultz) Danberg. She attended the University of California, Berkeley (B.A., 1957) and Columbia University (M.A., 1959, Ph.D., 1965).
MSS19980200
Biography
Ann Charters was born 10 November 1936, in Bridgeport, CT, the daughter of Nathan (a contractor) and Kate (Schultz) Danberg. She attended the University of California, Berkeley (B.A., 1957) and Columbia University (M.A., 1959, Ph.D., 1965). Charters career has included teaching creative writing at Colby Junior College, New London, NH (1961-63), working as an assistant editor at Random House-Knopf (1965) and continuing as an educator at Columbia University (instructor in literature, 1965-66), New York City Community College of Applied Arts and Sciences of the City University of New York (assistant professor of English (1967-70) and University of Connecticut (associate professor, 1974-81, professor of English, 1981-). She has been awarded fellowships from Columbia University (1958-59, 1963-64, 1965-66) and grants from the University of Connecticut (1975-76, 1981, 1983, 1984, 1986). Charters is a member of International PEN and Phi Beta Kappa.
Scope and Content
The collection contains typescripts and correspondence with contributors to Charter's compilation of
Dictionary of Literary Biography, Volume 16: The Beats: Literary Bohemians in Postwar America ( Detroit: Gale, 1983
). Also included are 30 black and white, matted portraits of literary personalities that were displayed as an exhibition in the University Libraries (1981-1982) entitled "Beats & Others: Literary Photographs 1966-1981" by Ann Charters.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to American literature. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Charter's Listening Night 2000-0105.vr1
Arrangement
The holdings of Archives and Special Collections includes the publications, manuscripts and correspondence of many of the individuals included in the biography. Please consult with a staff member for specific information.
Bibliography
American Literary Scholarship: An Annual, Duke University Press, 1983.
Chicago Tribune Book World, September 2, 1979.
Choice,, July/August, 1973.
Library Journal, May 1, 1979.
Newsweek, April 2, 1973.
New York Times, September 6, 1979.
New York Times Book Review, April 15, 1973.
New York Times Book Review,, July 15, 1979.
Poetry Project, April/May, 1987.
Saturday Review, July 7, 1979.
Time, July 30, 1979.
Times Literary Supplement, November 23, 1979.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Charters, Ann.
Subjects:
American literature--20th century--Biography.
Document Types:
Typescripts.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.
Occupations:
Author.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The literary portraits were purchased for the collection at the time of their exhibition.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Dictionary of Literary Biography, Volume 16: The Beats: Literary Bohemians in Postwar America,undated, 1980-1982
  - Introduction, 1980 (Box 1:1)
  - Baraka, Amiri (LeRoi Jones), 1980 (Box 1:2)
  - Blackburn, Paul, 1980 (Box 1:3)
  - Bremser, Bonnie, undated (Box 1:4)
  - Bremser, Ray, undated (Box 1:5)
  - Brossard, Chandler, undated (Box 1:6)
  - Burroughs, William S., 1982 (Box 1:7)
    - Notes: Burroughs and Huncke (Box 1:8)
  - Carroll, Paul, undated (Box 1:9)
  - Cassady, Carolyn, undated (Box 1:10)
  - Cassady, Neal, undated (Box 1:11)
  - Clausen, Andy, undated (Box 1:12)
  - Corso, Gregory, 1981 (Box 1:13)
  - Creeley, Robert, undated (Box 1:14)
  - DiPrima, Diane, undated (Box 1:15)
  - Doyle, Kirby, undated (Box 1:16)
  - Duncan, Robert, undated (Box 1:17)
  - Duncan, Robert, undated (Box 1:18)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus), 1981 (Box 1:19)
  - Everson, William (Brother Antoninus), undated (Box 1:20)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, undated (Box 1:21)
  - Gusin, Brion, undated (Box 1:22)
  - Huncke, Herbert, undated (Box 1:23)
  - Joans, Ted, undated (Box 1:24)
  - Kandel, Lenore, undated (Box 1:25)
  - Kaufman, Bob, undated (Box 1:26)
  - Kerouac, Jan, undated (Box 1:27)
  - Kerouac, Jack, undated (Box 1:28)
  - Kesey, Ken, undated (Box 1:29)
  - Krim, Seymour, undated (Box 1:30)
  - Kupferberg, Tuli, undated (Box 1:31)
  - Kyger, Joanne, undated (Box 1:32)
  - Lamantia, Philip, undated (Box 1:33)
  - Leary, Timothy, undated (Box 1:34)
  - Landesman, Jay and Fran, undated (Box 1:35)
  - Lipton, Lawrence, undated (Box 1:36)
  - Marshall, Edward, undated (Box 1:37)
  - Mailer, Norman, 1981 (Box 1:38)
  - McClure, Joanna, undated (Box 1:39)
  - McClure, Michael, 1982 (Box 1:40)
  - Mead, Taylor, undated (Box 1:41)
  - Meltzer, David, undated (Box 1:42)
  - Micheline, Jack, 1980 (Box 1:43)
  - Montgomery, John, undated (Box 1:44)
  - Norse, Harold, undated (Box 1:45)
  - O'Hara, Frank, undated (Box 1:46)
  - Olson, Charles, undated (Box 1:47)
  - Orlovsky, Peter, undated (Box 1:48)
  - Patchen, Kenneth, undated (Box 1:49)
  - Perkoff, Stuart Z., undated (Box 1:50)
  - Plymell, Charles, undated (Box 1:51)
  - Plymell, Charles, undated (Box 1:52)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1982 (Box 1:53)
  - Rothenberg, Jerome, undated (Box 1:54)
  - Rumaker, Michael, undated (Box 1:55)
  - Sanders, Ed, undated (Box 1:56)
  - Snyder, Gary, undated (Box 1:57)
  - Solomon, Carl, undated (Box 1:58)
  - Spicer, Jack, undated (Box 1:59)
  - Upton, Charles, undated (Box 1:60)
  - Vega, Janine Pommy, 1981 (Box 1:61)
  - Wakoski, Diane, undated (Box 1:62)
  - Waldman, Anne, undated (Box 1:63)
  - Watts, Alan Wilson, undated (Box 1:64)
  - Welch, Lew, undated (Box 1:65)
  - Whalen, Philip, undated (Box 1:66)
  - Wieners, John, undated (Box 1:67)
  - Williams, William Carlos, undated (Box 1:68)
  - Photocopies of Proofs (incomplete), 1982 (Box 2:69)
- Series II: Photographs,undated, 1966-1981
  - Sanders, Ed (with daughter), 1966 (Box 2)
  - Blackburn, Paul, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Burroughs, William S., 1972 (Box 2)
  - Jack Kerouac's funeral, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Kerouac, Jack, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Allen, Donald, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Corso, Gregory, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Waldman, Anne and Brownstein, Michael, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Holmes, John Clellon, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Bremser, Ray, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Cassady, Carolyn, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Weiners, John, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Zukofsky, Louis, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Orlovsky, Peter, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Jack Kerouac's house, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Jack Kerouac's grave, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Eigner, Larry, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Looking through Olson's door, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Olson, Charles, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Olson's street, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Olson's apartment house, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Olson, Charles (close up), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Kerouac with his mother, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Brother Antoninus (William Everson), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Kerouac, Jack, undated (Box 3)
  - McClure, Michael, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Duncan, Robert, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Ferrini, Vincent, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Ginsberg, Allen (breakfast, Naropa Institute), 1981 (Box 3)
  - Allen Ginsberg on the telephone with Bob Dylan, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Ginsberg, Allen (reading), 1970 (Box 3)
  - Cherry Valley kitchen, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Jack Kerouac's birthplace, undated (Box 3)
  - Allen Ginsberg with his father (Louis Ginsberg), 1970 (Box 3)
  - Allen Ginsberg's farm, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1969 (Box 3)